The Vatican and the CIA, there's
obviously been interactions between the
two parties in the past.
>> Starting after World War II, right? Um,
with like the Second Vatican Council, I
would assume they had a hand in a lot of
decisions that were made there.
>> Oh, I think even before that. It was
These These stories have been
declassified now and they're making for,
you know, great articles and movies, but
it was the Vatican that worked with the
CIA to translate a copy of Doctor
Zhivago into Russian. It was written in
English, translated into Russian,
and then put it in the Vatican
um, tent at the International Book Fair
in 1959,
so that
Russians who'd been approved to come
outside of Russia to the Book Fair could
see it,
tear it into, you know, bunches of of
pages, tape the pages to their legs,
put their clothes back on, and smuggle
them back into the Soviet Union.
And that was all a joint CIA Vatican
operation.
>> So, the CIA and the Vatican obviously
are working together against Russia, it
seems, communism at the time, which
>> Oh, yeah. Um, and the same kind of thing
happened uh in uh 1978
with the the decision to elevate John
Paul II to Pope.
>> Okay.
>> Uh, he was most definitely certainly the
CIA choice because he was Polish. There
had never been a Polish Pope, and we
really, really wanted to pressure the
Soviet Union. Uh,
Solidarity, the the labor union in
Poland, was rising up on strike at the
Gdansk shipyards at the time, and we
needed a Pole
who was strong enough to face down, to
stare down the Soviets, and John Paul
was the only one.
So, yeah, the US government and the CIA
were instrumental in pressuring the
College of Cardinals to choose John Paul
as the Pope.
>> How exactly do they pressure the College
of Cardinals? Is it through bribery? Is
it
>> No, no, no, it's nothing so crude.
They're all They're all patriots for
Catholicism and for the countries that
they come from.
And so
you know, to become a cardinal, you have
to be pretty doggone smart to to begin
with and very, very political.
And so they're reading the papers every
day. They know that the Soviet Union's
on the brink of invading Poland and
overthrowing the Jaruzelski government
and you know, arresting Lech Wałęsa and
you know, I mean, they tried to shoot
the Pope, didn't they? Or the Bulgarians
did. We'll never really know what the
true story was there.
Um
so we just go and we say, "Listen, if
you want to help crash the Soviet Union,
this is what you need to do."
>> Wow.
>> Mhm.
>> Very interesting.
There's also I heard you talk about in
another show with um
another popular Orthodox YouTuber,
Operation Gladio.
>> Yeah.
>> Can you tell us a little bit about that?
>> Yeah, Operation Gladio, it's funny to
me. Operation Gladio just seemed so
basic and so, you know, entry-level.
It I was always surprised that it took
as long as it did to come out and to be
declassified. But what it was was a
decision by the US government
to leave people behind
in a lot of the countries that were
liberated in the Second World War just
in case
somebody needed to start an uprising
um
against the Soviet Union is really what
it came down to. And so there were CIA
assets, in some cases CIA officers, who
were left behind all over Europe, mostly
Eastern Europe.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Interesting. And did that play any role
in Italy specifically with
>> Italy was the very first place that it
played a role.
>> Interesting.
>> So
in the election of 19 It was either '48
or '49. I I always
I always get confused. '48 or '49 was
the the CIA's his first covert action
program.
So, they um
they were authorized by Congress to
spend $150,000 to steal the Italian
election.
>> Mhm.
>> The communists were leading in the
polls. Now, it's not sophisticated, it's
not sexy, it's not something special out
of James Bond. All they did is they took
the $150,000 and they bribed Italian
reporters to write pro-conservative
articles in the Italian media.
>> Okay.
>> And so,
the journalists did that and the
conservative Christian Democratic Party
just barely edged out the communists.
The communists were more popular. The
communists were likely going to win that
election. And in the end, the
conservatives won it.
>> Very interesting. And [clears throat] on
this topic of the CIA influencing
parties and groups within the United
States,
um how does the government influence or
rather
uh interact with other religious
denominations and organizations such as
>> That's a good question.
>> Yeah.
>> That's kind of a tough question. There
is this
um
oh, how should I say it? There's this uh
there's this respect in the intelligence
community for Mormons, the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
>> Okay.
>> Of course, as Orthodox,
we don't really consider them to be a
Christian denomination, but
God bless, whatever.
The reason why there's such closeness is
that most Mormons go on a mission for a
year or 2 years
around the time that they're 18 or 19
years old.
And the Mormon Church is very, very good
about sending them to intensive
language training before they go. And
they'll they'll teach you in the
language of anywhere you're going. I
worked with a guy in Bahrain. He was a
He was the US Information Service
Officer from the State Department. And
um
he was Mormon, but he did his
mission in in Monte Carlo of all places.
Wow. Monte Carlo, can you imagine?
Uh but then what happens if you end up
getting sent to Tajikistan
>> Right.
>> or Madagascar
or, you know, Vietnam or whatever.
They send you to learn the language of
that country. And sometimes
the language training is as long as the
mission. It can even be longer than the
mission. So, Mormons come out of their
mission
um already having these really difficult
languages.
And um
and they don't do anything. They don't
smoke, they don't drink, they don't
gamble, they don't do drugs, they don't
lie, they don't even eat chocolate or
drink coffee.
And so they easily pass a polygraph and
a background investigation. You don't
have to train them and train them in the
language because they already have it,
and they can just step right into the
job.
>> So, they become an asset instantly to
the CIA.
>> officer he officer
>> Oh yeah, yeah. I see what you mean.
>> an asset of the agency, yeah.
>> Right. Right. And would you say that the
CIA like the CIA or the government pays
special interest to Orthodox groups in
North America? Does that happen?
>> There are a lot of Orthodox in the
intelligence community.
>> Okay.
>> I'm not sure why.
Um maybe it's cuz we don't do anything
bad. You know, who knows? I don't know.
But there was a gigantic
group of Greek Americans at the at the
CIA.
>> Okay.
>> Which I was always very proud of.
The US government does involve itself in
Orthodox politics, which I think is
absolutely horrid.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
the State Department under Hillary
Clinton was instrument instrumental in
splitting off the Ukrainian Orthodox
Church from the Russian Orthodox Church
after a thousand years.
>> Yeah.
>> And so now there's this I mean, for lack
of a better term, there's a schism
within the Orthodox Church that was
created by the US government.
That was a mistake.
>> Mhm. Given that situation, do you think
the government pays special attention to
say the Russian Orthodox Church outside
of Russia, the OCA, pro-Russian
churches?
>> There was a delegation of Ukrainian
Orthodox who went to Capitol Hill a
couple of months ago.
And after their visit
some members of Congress, mostly very
hardcore right-wing Republicans on
Capitol Hill, made provocative
statements against the Russian Orthodox
Church saying it was not a religion, it
was a branch of the Russian military,
that the patriarch was a criminal, just
terrible things, terrible things. And
they speak like they know, like with
authority.
But yeah, it's it was a mistake to be
involved.